[music]
>> With that faithful, happy draft week,
I'm your 49ers team reporter Briana
Janelle sitting down with our digital
editor Brooke Evans [music] on the
saloon presented by Cisco. Now, we've
got a lot of action for you today in
this podcast episode. We've got guests
from KNBR, ESPN, and there was a lot
happening over here at 49. 49. And so,
we've got John Lynch doing his opening
press [music] conference before the
draft. We've got our guys in the
building for phase one of OTAs. But
Brooke, let's dive just straight into
it. Everything that our president of
football operations and general manager
John Lynch had to say before we kick off
the draft. First off, we've got some
exciting news. John Lynch did announce
and he confirmed that the team has had
an agreement with future Hall of Fame
left tackle Trent Williams. Now, the
team has yet to announce the signing of
a contract extension, but great news to
hear that there are some agreements
there to have Trent be a part of this
team for the foreseeable future.
>> So exciting. And you know, on that
topic, John Lynch did say that it
doesn't really change their draft
approach. They always expected Trent to
be here. So, now it's really just about
best player available. That's right. So,
before we dive into everything draft, it
was phase one of OTAs. Just to give the
faithful a little bit of context on what
phase one looks like for the 49ers or
across the league. These are voluntary
workouts. So, the players are not
required to be here in the building for
those workouts. They are completely It's
completely up to them whether they want
to come in the building or not. There's
no penalty there. But John Lynch didn't
have any exact number of how many guys
on the roster showed up for these
workouts because he is super busy with
something happening this weekend in the
draft. But he did pop in and our media
team was there to see all the guys come
in the building. And he said that it was
a really good turnout. He didn't have a
number for us, but he said, quote, "Darn
near whole." So, pretty much the whole
team
showed up for OTAs this week. Now, let's
get into draft. Brooke, what were some
of your insights from John Lynch as you
work your way to Thursday? Yeah, I mean,
also on OTAs, just a lot of smiling
faces in the building, too. So, it was
really good to see all these smiling
faces back together and see them.
>> like football.
>> It does. It feels like football is right
around the corner, which it is. So, but
speaking on the presser yesterday, it
was really important the things that he
said. Um and I think we got really good
nuggets out of that. Starting with bus
best player available mindset, Lynch
made it pretty clear that it doesn't
feel like this team has glaring needs.
So, they're in a position to really just
take the best player available as the
board falls. Also, he did say that there
were fewer true first-round grades this
year compared to last. So, that can make
things really interesting when picking
at number 27. But speaking of picking at
number 27, we are just slated to pick
there. So, come draft day, anything can
happen. And right now with only six
picks, I mean, he didn't shy away from
the idea of possible trades. He's been
talking to teams. So, saying that we're
open to ways to finding more. He said,
"We don't have a ton of picks. How can
we find some more?" Yeah, definitely.
So,
I loved this press conference for the
faithful because they got to see what's
going on in John Lynch's head before the
49ers actually make the calls come
Thursday through Saturday. That doesn't
mean that John Lynch is going to put all
of their cards out on the table. This is
the draft and you have to do have to
conceal some things. But you've got to
see a little bit of the mindset that
John Lynch is carrying into this draft.
With the best guy available at number
27, it's later in the first round. So,
you're doing a bit of a dance honestly
with every single draft pick throughout
this draft is that you're dancing
between that long-term impact versus
that short-term impact. The guy who can
really have an influence on the game
come week one when we start over in
Australia? Or is this an investment in
the 49ers future? And this is a guy that
they want to develop over the course of
a few seasons and we really see him
shine later on in his career. So, you
never really know when it comes to these
picks. But honestly, every team during
this draft is trying to find the best
guy. And it's going to be a competition
amongst 32 teams on who has the better
draft portfolio at the end of the day.
And you don't know that until we've
actually seen these guys perform on the
field. So, if you know, a ton of work
goes into the analysis of these guys.
Our scouting team has worked endlessly
to know everything there is to know
about these guys and to pick the best
guy on the board at number 27. Again,
there were a few questions to John Lynch
about possible trade scenarios. And
again, John Lynch isn't going to share
what the 49ers plan is on Thursday. But
I feel like we got a few hints there
from John. And really, he said that the
team is going to stay malleable. And
that they're going to have an open
mindset in this draft and they're going
to be hearing out pretty much everyone.
And he thinks that there's going to be a
lot of movement this year. He sees teams
moving up in the draft and that could
come up as a scenario where maybe a team
calls the 49ers, likes their pick, wants
to move up. But there might also be a
scenario where the 49ers are open to
really anything. And if they see fit the
opportunity to move up and grab a player
that they really like, they're open to
doing that. With that being said, the
49ers only have six picks versus 11 last
year. So, not as much stock to work
with. But he thinks, you know, if it
does make sense to find some more picks,
they're certainly be open to that. So,
John Lynch is open to the idea of
trading either out of the first round,
which it sounds a little bit more
realistic with the stock that they have,
or possibly moving up if there's a
player that they see possibly fall down
and they want to go for. So, really, I
think John Lynch told the media and told
the faithful on Monday that we're open
to anything. And so, it's a time to, you
know,
call out to the other teams and be like,
"Hey, my phone is open."
>> [laughter]
>> My phone is open for Thursday through
Saturday. So, who knows what the 49ers
will do, who they will pick at number
27, if they will pick at 27. A lot to
look out for as we work our way to
Thursday.
>> Definitely. And And then the last thing
I also thought was really interesting a
part of this presser. He says that
they're using AI to run draft
simulations, which I think is so cool.
Really fitting for Silicon Valley. And
he says to quote, "If you aren't using
it, you're behind." And I think that's
pretty cool to just think about, you
know, the ways that we've progressed in
the strategy and the form that we're
using to build this draft. And all to
your point said being said as well is
you really never know till they get out
there on the field, right? So, um
excited to see how this whole draft
unfolds and really just to see these new
faces come to the building.
>> Yeah, it sounds like a fun game. I would
want to be in the draft room for those
draft simulator AI games that they got
going on. Imagine like you get to have
this AI algorithm that's picking at as
the Cardinals, as the Rams, as whoever.
And you get to see the picks that are
being made before you and then you feel
the pressure of all the different
scenarios that could happen. So, they're
staying ready so they don't have to get
ready this Thursday. And I think that
sounds like a lot of fun. Also, I want
to be in that draft room because Raheem
Morris sounds like a time.
>> does. Cool parties left and right. He
was just saying that.
>> Lynch was talking about this really fun
story of how Raheem Morris contributes
to the draft room and sort of the
influence that he'll have on the picks
that the 49ers make. And he goes, "You
know what? If a guy is in our building,
he is going to have an influence on the
picks we make because that is a part of
his job. And it's a true team effort
when it comes to who is making these
picks on draft night." But he's like,
"You know what? You know why I love
Raheem Morris? It's because he really
adds to the room. He never takes away
from the room. He has a ton of energy.
He's worked with John. He's worked with
Kyle in the past. And he's got this
one-liner going on that he's saying
like, "If we draft this guy, I am
throwing a pool party." So, I'm
expecting a ton of pool parties from
Raheem this summer. And I think it's
going to be a lot of fun seeing what
they all do.
>> Definitely. He seems like a great guy.
John Lynch also said he's a bundle of
energy. He's curious and he's
insightful. Sounds like great things to
have as your DC. So, uh super exciting
things. We also heard from Brock Purdy
and Fred Warner, which is so nice just
to see familiar faces back in front of
the media again. Again, they were all
smiling and good mood. Uh Brock Purdy
said that he's feeling in a really good
spot physically after dealing with his
turf toe injury last season. So, always
great things to hear that from your
franchise quarterback. Um he also spoke
about Mike Evans and how excited he is
to work with him. He said, as a
quarterback,  you dream of those
one-on-one opportunities in the red
zone. I loved hearing the story about
how he found out the news that Mike
Evans was going to be his teammate and
how that news broke. So, Brock Purdy was
working with his tight end George Kittle
out in Nashville at George Kittle's own
training facility. It's like this barn
he's got going on with a ton of workout
equipment. And he's got a football field
with the George Kittle Matt Luchador
mask. Like it is really cool what he's
got going on in Nashville. But he was
working out with Brock Purdy and George
was scheming up with him. He was like,
"Dude, we've got to add Mike Evans to
this offense. How awesome would that
be?" So, it sounds like he was a little
bit in the forefront of that, you know,
behind the works of getting him here. Uh
I We definitely know that he was like a
closer in that conversation where he was
making the call to Mike Evans and
telling him how awesome the culture is
that out here and how awesome that it
would be to have on this team. But Brock
Purdy was giving us a little bit behind
the scenes of everything that was going
on with the signing. But he was actually
with George when the news broke. They
had the TV up in the barn where they got
all the workout equipment. And he saw
the news broke and they were just so
hyped to see Mike Evans be a part of
their new offense.
>> Yeah, I mean, what can't Brock Purdy and
George Kittle do? They're salesmen now.
I mean, I love it. And it doesn't
surprise me at all that George Kittle
has his friends and connections from all
across the country.
Um and it was really cool to hear also
Mike Evans speak on how George Kittle
had that call with him and really
influenced him. He recently spoke on
Fred Warner's podcast, The Real Ones,
kind of about that and in his decision
to come here to the Bay, one Bay to
another Bay. So, um definitely go check
that one out. It's super cool. But
speaking on Fred Warner, he also spoke
yesterday. So, on the defensive side,
Fred Warner is back with no
restrictions. We love to hear that. He
said he's feeling extremely blessed and
ready to jump right into the off-season.
Obviously, we're approaching draft, but
there's a lot more to come after draft.
So, seeing these leaders back in the
building, really excited to jump in, is
just all good things.
>> A healthy Fred Warner, we love to see.
He was just talking about how antsy he
is to play football and to get back out
there on the field because he went
through his recovery all last season. He
felt like he was ready to go right
towards the tail end of the season. So,
he's like, "Guys, I've been itching to
get out there on the field for so long."
And he's got to wait a little bit for
week one and we get out there in
training camp. I'm sure when pads come
on, he's the loudest out there on the
field and he is the most, I mean,
excited.
>> Right. I mean, I'm sure the whole team
is the hyped, but once the pads come on,
Fred is ready. And it's going to be even
more fun this year because he's got his
bestie, Drake Greenlaw, with him. And I
loved hearing the story of how Drake
gave him the call. We got to hear from
Fred Warner's side of the story
before Drake signed. He called up Fred
Warner. He's like, "Hey, man, I'm back
in the Bay, back with my family." And
so, it's just fun to see all the
friendships blossoming. Yeah, so sweet.
Fred Warner's going to have to fly all
the way down to Australia to finally get
his pads back on and really ready to
play, but I'm sure he's just going to
absolutely tear it up and so excited to
watch them in week one. And for the rest
of the season. But speaking of which, we
are in draft week and you just completed
your last mock draft. How exciting.
>> That's right. The final mock draft
before the real thing. This was the last
Monday. I was, you know, scouring the
internet and finding what all the
analysts had to say that the 49ers are
predicted maybe to do from Thursday to
Saturday. And this one is a lot of fun
because we've got a few analysts on here
who mocked every single pick the 49ers
are scheduled to make this weekend. So,
from round one to round four, we've got
nfl.com's Chad Reuter and ESPN's Jordan
Reed. They went through the whole slate
and they mocked a name for each pick the
49ers are scheduled for. So, you know
what? I'm just going to run down the
list and go through them. First up,
nfl.com's Chad Reuter. At round one,
pick number 27, the 49ers select Caleb
Lomu, an offensive tackle out of Utah.
Now, we've seen this name sporadically
as we work our way into the draft. We
talked about him last week and how he'd
be a fit on this offense, but a pretty,
um, I would say consensus pick from
analysts across the league. They think
we're going to go Caleb Lomu, should we
pick at number 27. Now, in round two,
pick number 58, Jeremy Bernard, a wide
receiver out of Alabama. Moving on to
round four, pick number 127, V J Payne,
a safety from Kansas State. Staying in
round four here, pick number 133, LT
Overten, finally, an edge rusher from
Alabama. Pick number 138, Jude Bowery,
offensive tackle from Boston College.
Finally, with the last pick in the NFL
draft, pick number 139, back-to-back.
138, 139. But this guy is U R Bernard,
defensive tackle. Now, this one's really
interesting because he doesn't have a
college. Right there, I was going to say
what his college is, but he's actually a
part of the NFL's International Player
Pathway Program. He's originally from
Nigeria, but he performed at the HBCU
Combine and he was he had an outstanding
performance. He broke multiple HBCU
Combine records and so, he was really
put on the league's status when it comes
to draft week. He's on some analyst
radar there, for sure.
He hasn't played a single snap of
football game. So, it's kind of crazy.
>> played a single snap of football.
However, don't let that get you strayed
from how athletic this guy is and how
much of a performance he can have on a
football field. He's been training. I've
seen that he's been watching YouTube
videos on all the drills and skills. And
so, he really showed out at the HBCU
Combine in March. And so, I'm excited to
see where he falls in this draft.
>> Yeah. Now, ESPN's Jordan Reed, going
back up to round one, here's what Jordan
Reed thinks the 49ers are going to do
this weekend. Now, round one, pick
number 27, it's Malakai Lawrence, the
edge rusher from the University of
Central Florida. Now, in round two, pick
number 58, this is one I think George
Kittle is going to like. It's a Hawkeye,
Jennings Dunker, an offensive guard from
Iowa. You know, George loves his
O-linemen.
>> [laughter]
>> Now, moving on to the final four picks
in round four. Pick number 127, Charles
Dimings, a cornerback from Stephen F.
Austin. Now, pick number 133, we got
Cyrus Allen, a wide receiver from
Cincinnati. Pick number 138, one John
Lynch I think would like, Bud Clark, a
safety from TCU. And pick number 139,
Demetrius Crownover, offensive tackle,
Texas A&M. All right. Ah, you got it
through.
>> That was a lot of names, but those are
the picks that a lot of the analysts
think the 49ers are going to make this
weekend.
>> I love it. And I love to hear from all
our analysts and they've been doing so
much back-end work to really lead up to
this draft. And it's exciting cuz the
day is finally here. And we actually
have a few guests on the podcast that
are going to give us our very last
insights before the draft.
>> That's right. All right, faithful. Next
up, we've got ESPN's Nick Wagoner and
Guy Haberman from KNBR. Hey, there are.
All right, faithful, joining us on the
saloon is Nick Wagoner from ESPN. Nick,
it's draft week. How are you feeling?
Good, good. Ready to get it going and,
uh, move on to the next thing. Right.
That's right. Okay, so, first question
right off the bat, I want to know what
would you want the 49ers to do at pick
number 27 versus what do you think John
Lynch is going to do in round one?
Yeah, no, not that anybody really cares
what what I want to do, but, uh, I think
I think the thing for them it actually
probably aligns with what they're
looking to do. And and I've been kind of
banging this drum for a while where
they're in a position they just need to
find stars, which is easy to say cuz
everyone does, right? Like everyone in
the league wants to draft the best
players possible. That's the whole
objective. But this is a team, you know,
John Lynch was talking about yesterday
that they're not a ton of like really
pressing positional needs. But their
biggest need to me is figuring out who
is the next nucleus of guys that they
can build around. What is who are the
next foundational players? Because you
have so many guys, George Kittle and
Christian McCaffrey and Trent Williams
and and all those guys who are closer to
the end than they are at the beginning
of their career and they have been such
a a foundational part of this franchise
for so long, but eventually you're going
to have to have other guys ready to step
in. And I think Brock Purdy, obviously,
is one of those guys that you know. I
think Deomodore Deomodore Lenoir
probably falls into that category. But
after that, you you're you're kind of
looking for that next generation of
guys. And so, if they can make that
happen and align that with maybe a
position that they do somewhat need and
and that could be an edge rusher, it
could be a receiver, whatever it is, I
think that would probably be the ideal
scenario. That's a lot easier said than
done, particularly when you're picking
at number 27, but the draft is such a
crapshoot anyway, there's no way to know
that. So, um, to me, I think what the
what the Niners will do is probably look
for the best player available at
position
defensive line, edge rusher
specifically, wide receiver, or even
offensive line where you start planning
for the future and and find an heir
apparent to Trent Williams. Yeah, you
mentioned yesterday in a tweet the idea
of taking someone who maybe might not
start right away, like an offensive
tackle behind Trent Williams, versus
taking someone who might make an impact
right away, like say an edge. What are
the pros and cons of doing either or in
those scenarios?
Yeah, I I think what you what you value
there is is it goes back to the
conversation of who can be that next
star that, you know, you could maybe you
could find an edge rusher. And I use
this example a lot, particularly when it
comes to the draft and you're drafting
toward the end of the round because if
you're if you're drafting there, a lot
of times positional value becomes such a
big part of the conversation. And so,
teams value edge rushers and tackles and
wide receivers so much that when you're
drafting that late, you might get the
seventh or eighth best guy at that
position. Now, that's just what it looks
like on paper. They could turn out to be
the best, which is what the ideal
scenario is. Or, you may end up drafting
a safety or a guard who could be the
first or second best guy at that
position. And then you have to kind of
factor in where that positional value
plays into that. So, I think the 49ers
are in an interesting spot just because
they obviously want to compete this
year. Everything that they've done to
this point off in the off-season tells
you that they're ready to compete this
year. So, you have to figure what type
of contribution are we going to get from
this guy? And does it come at the
expense of a guy who maybe isn't going
to play a lot, but long-term will have
more value to us and could be one of
those guys that I was just talking about
where he is a foundational player. A a
left tackle. You're Trent
John Lynch used the phrase premium
position talking about offensive tackle
a few times yesterday. And so, to me, I
think those are kind of the the things
that you have to weigh. And I don't know
that there's a right or wrong answer as
long as you're getting the best guy. Um,
but so much of that is how does he
project? How much do can our coaching
staff, how much do we believe in our
coaching staff to get the best out of
this guy? And our scheme? The Niners,
obviously, are in a really good position
in terms of the coaching staff. So, they
have to feel good about whoever they
bring in. But those are all the factors
that kind of go into the pot that you
have to figure out. And oh, by the way,
there's 26 teams in front of you that
can throw off any plan that you have
going in, uh, which also makes it really
difficult to discern. Yeah, I mean, look
at all the stars on our team that were
drafted either in the fifth round or
later. So, you never know the value that
they have on draft day versus what could
turn out over the course of a few
seasons. Now, I want to talk about the
chances of a trade scenario in the first
round. Say the 49ers are flexible and
they can move either up or possibly out
of round one. What are the chances there
and how would that impact the
significance of the picks that the 49ers
make? Yeah, I I think certainly, you
know, you're John Lynch talking about
they they have to be kind of malleable,
I think is the word he used. A good
word, by the way.
And and but talking about just being
able to go either way. But my read on
the situation is cuz cuz Lynch referred
to it a couple times, it's not a secret.
They only have six picks. I think they'd
probably like to have a few more. I know
for a fact they would like to get a
third round pick, get back into those
kind of middle rounds because a lot of
people you talk to around the league
tell you that this draft is maybe not
super deep in first round guys, but
second and third and fourth round guys,
there's a big clump of guys. So the more
picks that you have in there, the
better. Obviously they traded their
third round pick for a defensive tackle
who should help them a lot this year,
but I I think moving down would be an
ideal scenario, but again,
it it comes back to what does a team
want? Who do teams want to come up to
get? Generally you will see, you know,
oh there's a quarterback if if we want
to get a a guy who's maybe a second
round quarterback prospect, but you can
move back into the first round, it gives
you a fifth round option on that guy.
And I will say in this draft, it doesn't
seem like there's a lot of quarterbacks
that are going to go very high. Fernando
Mendoza we know is going to go number
one. After that, Ty Simpson from Alabama
is is considered like a late first round
pick, early second round pick. You've
got three teams, you know, the Dolphins,
the Cardinals, the the um Who am I
missing here off the top of my head? The
Jets, those are those are teams that
that could be in the mix for a
quarterback and may need to leapfrog
each other. So I think maybe there's
something that could come into play
there, you know, I don't know if how I'm
willing the Niners would be to do a
trade in the division, but something
like that I don't think would be
outrageous and I wouldn't be that
unusual. So um I think that's their best
bet and their best hope to to find
something like that and and I think it
would be ideal just because you heard
John Lynch say it's less than 20 the
number of players they have with first
round grades. The chances of one of the
guys who has a first round grade making
it to number 27 are probably pretty slim
and so um if you're going to be drafting
a guy that you have graded as a second
rounder, you'd probably prefer to draft
him in the second round particularly if
you can add more draft capital on top of
that. Right. And you know, in this off
season during free agency, we had a
successful free agency where we're
adding a lot of guys here. We had a lot
of guys return. And given the state of
this roster and how this team is built
right now, what's something that would
actually surprise you come Thursday
night?
Oh boy. What would surprise me? Um
I I don't get surprised by a lot
anymore. I've been doing this for
[laughter] a long time. It's the NFL
draft. Yeah, yeah. I mean I'd I'd be
surprised if um
I'd be surprised if they moved up, I
would say, if they traded up. Now now
that's not it wouldn't be outrageous. I
if they moved up more than like a couple
spots, let's say, I would be surprised
by. Um again, just going back to the
lack of draft capital, but like I just
said a minute ago, you know, if they
only have, let's say, 16, 15 guys with a
first round grade and one of those guys
happens to linger to 23 or 24 and
there's a big gap between who that
player is and who may be next on on your
board or that you the options you would
be looking at if you stayed at 27, um
you can't rule it out. I never say
never, but I guess I would be a little
bit surprised if they moved up um
because it would be a two a two factor
surprise. One that they moved up, but
two because it would mean somebody that
we weren't expecting to fall uh probably
fell into that range, too. All right.
Well, you've shared as we worked our way
up to the draft that the 49ers are well
positioned to add a wide receiver during
this draft class. What qualities are the
49ers looking for in a wide receiver
draft pick that already wasn't added
during the off season like Mike Evans or
Christian Kirk? So what type of
qualities are in this new guy that
possibly might get drafted? I I think to
me the the word that comes to mind is
juice. Uh they need they need a speed
they need speed and and that doesn't
mean a guy who runs a 42 40 or a 43 40.
That stuff is all fine and dandy, but it
is how quickly can you separate? Um you
know, can you create separation at the
top of your route? Those types of things
that give them an opportunity to get
yards after catch. As we know this
offense is built around a lot of that
and it hasn't been there the last couple
years. That that hasn't prevented them
from being productive, but I think when
you look at the just the way the offense
is set up right now, that's something
that's lacking is is just that kind of
top end speed, a guy who can catch, you
know, a 15 yd dig route and turn it into
a 70 yd touchdown.
Um that I think that would be something
that they would really like and
honestly, again, this kind of goes back
to the the the beginning of our
conversation here where you have to
start thinking about the future a little
bit. You know, Christian Kirk is here on
a one year deal. Mike Evans signed a
four year deal, but effectively it's a
one year deal and they can kind of
figure it out from there, but um you
know, you don't you don't necessarily
have the the long term options at that
position, either. And and so that's
really what a lot of this is and I know
it's so easy to get caught up in
who's the guy that can help right away
and win you a Super Bowl. Picking at 27,
it's just hard to find that anyway. It's
hard to find it in the draft period, but
but picking that late is hard anyway. So
um if you can find a guy like you know,
Indiana's Omar Cooper, I think is a guy
that's really interesting because of the
different ways he can be used. We've
seen the 49ers have success with Deebo
Samuel who is the guy that he gets
compared to a lot and the nice thing
about that is is you can get him the
ball in different ways. He doesn't just
have to be a slot receiver or an X
receiver. He can you know, you can put
him in the backfield even or you can you
know, you can do all kinds of different
things where he can give you short term
impact, but the long term impact would
be even greater. And so I think I think
just finding some speed, finding some
juice at at wide receiver would would
give them a different element um and
kind of open things up a little bit more
for some of the other guys underneath,
too. All right. Investing in the future.
Nick, thank you so much for all of your
expert 49ers and draft insight. We
appreciate you coming on and happy draft
week.
Yeah, you too. We'll see you soon. Take
care. Now joining us on the saloon is
our guy Habes, Guy Haberman from KNBR is
joining us now. Habes, how are you and
happy draft week? Bree, great to see
you. I need I need your nickname uh
since you're calling me Habes now and
and and [laughter] It's Bree. It's Bree
the nickname. Bree and Brooke.
Or you call us B&B. B&B, I like that.
Okay. Done.
Beautiful. Now I want to hear your
thoughts on this off season. Some of the
wins that John Lynch pulled into the
4949. Yeah, I mean uh well, I think the
first wins was like seeing Fred Warner
on Monday talking about how no
restrictions, right? And George Kittle
looking like
um things are going well for him. And
obviously Trent Williams coming back
into the fold and having another full
off season of of health for Brock Purdy
and all that. Also Arik Armstead,
uh I think is definitely the headliner
on defense and Mike Evans the headliner
on offense. Like those are big time
headliners. I love the way Kyle Shanahan
said it the at the um
uh league meetings, like guys who've
been there before definitely still have
something in the tank. Arik Armstead
definitely has something still in the
tank, like a a big time player. And Mike
Evans, the beauty of Mike Evans is his
game has not even though he was and came
in the league a very fast player, um but
he doesn't have to have separation in
order to make big time plays. The Niners
always are near the top of the league in
kind of explosive plays, but they're not
necessarily straight line down the
sideline balls and maybe Mike Evans can
bring some of that, too. Yeah, and you
touched on a little bit. Our leaders
have gotten healthy in the off season.
The off season is so important when it
comes to recovery and we've had so many
great positive updates on injuries and
health. Um just kind of given the state
of where we're at now, what do you make
of it and maybe some of the crazy
workouts we've seen happening in the off
season?
I mean it's you know, the McCaffrey
Yeah. [laughter]
Right. That one, like that's one of
those you know, when you get tricked by
AI videos and then sometimes you see a
real video and you're like,
no. What is that? What is that? It's
Christian McCaffrey being Christian
McCaffrey. So um you know, he's at the
top of the list of
>> Yeah. workload every off season. We talk
about it every season. We talk about it.
So easy to say, well, maybe a few less
touches this time around and then you
get into the games and you go, how could
he have less touches? He's the best
player on the field. And he's another
guy, like as the year went on,
he just got better and better and
better. Um
So you know, his health is obviously
paramount, but uh getting Dre Greenlaw,
I mean we didn't mention him, right? If
he has a healthy season, what an add
that is. So
uh there's it's it's the same story
every year. It was obviously the big
story last year. It's the it's that
story it's that way around the league
uh with everybody. Like can you be
healthy enough
um to allow your best players, the top
half of your roster to to be the
difference makers that they are cuz
these guys have
such significant difference makers.
Yeah. And we all know Christian
McCaffrey is AI. He's not human. It was
it came out when we saw the screws going
into his head during that one playoff
game. But uh definitely fun to see all
the guys getting back into true form and
seeing their health come along as we
work our way to the 2026 season. But as
we transition from 2025 to 2026, Habes,
it is draft week. What do you think are
some of the biggest needs the 49ers need
to address this Thursday through
Saturday? They can't have enough D-line.
I mean that's always the case and that's
definitely on the list. Um you know, but
edge is tough. Edge is tough late in the
first round. I know Bree you talked to
Daniel Jeremiah
the other day and I saw he said this
week that there's going to be a run on
on receivers and offensive lineman,
which it always feels like there's a run
on offensive lineman. The good news is
the the receiver group is pretty deep
and there are some players that can help
uh and we know that the Niners love to
you know, they love to kick the tires on
receivers sometimes in the first round,
sometimes later. So I I think that's
another position that you probably can't
have enough of um given, you know,
Christian Kirk is in and and Ricky
Pearsall, when healthy, was one of the
best receivers in the league last year.
Mike Evans,
because of the age, you have to be ready
for a game or two. So uh you can
definitely solidify that position.
Safety, always. Um it's not a quote
unquote premium position. I know John
Lynch had a laugh about that in his
press conference on Monday cuz you know,
it's not viewed as a quote unquote it's
not edge rusher or left tackle, but
uh the second you have a game changing
safety, it changes everything. So
another linebacker is definitely on my
list, too. Um and a guard. Now I know
they feel like they've solidified the
offensive line and they have, but I
think we've seen the last couple years a
guard, somebody who can play some tackle
um in the future, right? Maybe 3 years
from now if Trent Williams isn't back 3
years from now.
But that's a long way out. But you know,
I think left guard is definitely a top
priority and that's not necessarily a
first round pick.
And the good news is the Niners have
shown the ability to get guards with
value who can play right away in those
sort of middle rounds. Yeah, definitely.
A lot of fun things to unfold come draft
this Thursday. But given that the
players were back in 49 yesterday in the
state of what this team this roster is
now, where do you think the identity
lies? What's the identity of this team
given we have so many new guys coming in
for free agency and old guys returning?
Say we had to play a game this Sunday.
Right. Yeah,
>> [laughter]
>> being in another time zone or 18 hours
away, right? Um Who knows? Who knows?
But you know, I think it's interesting,
right? 2 years ago it was coming off of
a Super Bowl. How do you handle that?
Then it was coming off of a long off
season and you get sort of much needed
rest. And now hopefully what it is is
the happy medium of the hunger that
comes with not winning a championship,
but the inspiration that comes with
knowing you proved something last year,
you accomplished something last year
that that was a signal of overcoming
adversity, defying the odds, all that
sort of stuff. And they weren't a team
that had no expectations last year. They
had huge expectations coming into the
year as they always do. But you know, I
think that's kind of an interesting mix
of like this team especially
what they did in the regular season was
awesome.
Everything kind of got put over the top
after winning in Philadelphia.
And obviously the way it ended in
Seattle was really frustrating and
disappointing. And so you you always
end, however it ends, if it doesn't end
with a Lombardi, with the sour taste in
your mouth. But that was particularly
sour.
But like I to me the identity is a group
of guys who they're hungry to do it
and they know what it takes
and they still have the capability,
right? And that that's
called being in your prime. Those are
guys that are in their prime. And so
you know, I I think that's to me that's
the identity is like a team that's been
so close,
proved they still have a push in them
last year and hopefully they're inspired
to to give it a deep run again. Mhm. All
right, even though the draft is our
Super Bowl for our scouting team and for
our front office, the 49ers won't be
playing a game this weekend. But tell me
about your excitement for the 2026
season and what we've got cooking up for
a great season ahead, the 80th season.
>> the 80th season. 80th anniversary. 80th
anniversary. How great is that logo?
The Niners have always had
awesome, you know, like anniversary
logos and and obviously with Jerry, 80
is is very special.
An Australia trip, a Mexico trip. I
think just a really good schedule. Like
last year coming into the season was a
good schedule because people thought it
was the easiest schedule in the league.
This year's a good schedule for another
reason. This year's a good schedule
because you're like, God, these are
every week you're playing headline
opponents. So I don't know. It'll be I
think you know, the
I get very excited for the draft. I get
very excited for the schedule release.
We know
who you're playing. But to me the prime
time kind of slate is what really is
intriguing. And there's
you know, you don't need an excuse to
put the Niners on prime time.
But when you're playing the Cowboys,
that helps. What now is that going to
end up
you know, on Monday or Sunday Sunday
afternoon. There will have to be a
battle for that game.
So
that to me is just like every week these
it's it's so cliche. It's a heavyweight
fight and every game this team plays in
particular this franchise at home or on
the road is a prime time game
officially or unofficially. But this
year I think there's going to be a lot
of really premium games. Definitely. And
we're really excited over here as well.
But giving back to the draft and just
kind of looking ahead in this 2026
season, what's one thing that's going to
decide how far this team goes? That X
factor.
You mean other than health, Brooke? Yes,
other than health. I like that. I think
the thing that I've come into the the
year the last 2 years thinking about and
I think it applies again this year.
And it applies really every year because
we see now like Tom Brady was a great
example.
Quarterbacks in particular evolve as
they age.
When you're in your prime, you're still
getting better. Like think of anybody,
you, two, me,
everybody. Like if you're still in
competition, you are trying to improve.
And so for me one of the big stories
every year is you've had this still
young, now entering his physical prime
franchise quarterback. What incremental
improvements can Brock Purdy make this
year? You know, to get from where any
guy starts to where Purdy is, there's
only about there's 32 starters kind of,
you know,
Mike Sando's tiers list comes out and
usually half of those guys are on teams
that are trying to replace them. So
there's really like 15 quarterbacks in a
given year that have reached that
that little, you know, that that
exclusive top of the mountain.
And that's the that's really hard to
beat 99.9% of 99.8% I guess of everybody
else. And then what becomes really hard
is once you're kind of there, how do you
get just it's how do you get just a
little bit better? How do you get 1%
better?
And that's where the margins are really
thin and that's one drive at the end of
a must-win game and that's one throw and
that's the fourth quarter of the
playoffs in the cold of the rain. Like
that's where we really start. And so I
just get so excited the last few years
for you know, the chances cuz you don't
get many games to see Brock Purdy
in those situations and how he how he
continues to improve trying to get into
those situations and succeed in those
situations. I just think I just read
Seth Wickersham's book called
American Kings. It's the biography of
the quarterback.
It's excellent. And I mean the the
the quarterback position is without a
doubt the most to me the most
interesting thing in all of sports
because the margins are so thin and all
the ways it can go wrong, there's so
many. And all the ways they can go
right, there's so few. And so when you
get a guy who's your guy year in and
year out like Brock Purdy is for the
49ers, it's
it's the best drama there is. Yeah, and
he can ducky. What can't he do, right?
>> [laughter]
>> That's 100% right always for Brock Purdy
is hitting the ducky.
Sweet guy. Thank you so much for all of
your insight on the 49ers and the draft
as we work our way closer to the 2026
season. It should be a fun one and we're
excited to see more of you. All right,
Bree, Brooke, enjoy the draft. Thank
you. Have a good one. Thank you so much
for joining us on today's episode of
Saloon. It's the last one that we have
leading up to the draft. So make sure
you guys stay tuned for all our draft
coverage. We're going to have exclusive
interviews, articles and more coming all
to you. That's right. We're going to be
talking with every guy that gets drafted
to the 49ers and you don't want to miss
it. So make sure you subscribe to the
Saloon on YouTube, SiriusXM and all your
favorite podcast platforms. We'll see
you here very soon. Stay tuned and go
Niners.
>> [music]
[music]